My name is Mallen Clifton.
I'm a PhD candidate
at Stanford University.
Just about to start dissertation.
But this presentation is not about that.
It's about something different.
I'm interested in the latent space,
which is a pretty vague concept.
And so I'm using this work,
compressed cinema as a case study.
I might try to turn this into an article
or something.
So, you know, especially in terms of that.
But in general,
if y'all have any thoughts, comments,
critiques at the end,
I'd be happy to hear it.
So I'll just get started.
The main question I'm thinking about this,
especially in terms of the conference
theme, is how do we
how do we supervise the unsupervised,
right, the latent space that we know it
as this hidden structure
within large language models?
But it's not something
that you can actually understand
the workings of easily.
And even if you do get that data
to actually know how it works,
because there's so much information
there and it's very hard to understand,
like why things are actually configured
the way they are.
And so a more technical question
I'm asking is how do we understand
the function of the latent space in LMS
as a pertains to literary production?
And I do believe
this has pretty important ramifications.
Right.
People are reading AI generated
writing every day.
This is going to build
into larger pressures.
We started to think about,
you know, like worries about being able
to detect AI generated text
and questions around that.
And I think it also has larger
implications for meaning and intent in AI,
as it's further integrated into decision
making systems, really,
you know, on the scale of corporations,
even government,
the fact that we are seeing this text
every day, we need to understand
like how it's actually working.
And so it's really essential
to look at the latent space
if we want to answer these questions.
Why is that?
I have a few quotes
I pulled from Antonio Simone,
who offered his own writing,
A Theory of Latent Spaces.
He's actually mainly talking about it
in terms of visual culture.
And so I think it's interesting to
look at what he's saying,
but then try to translate that
into what I'm more interested
in terms of literary culture
and literary production.
So a few particular quotes that I thought
were especially interesting.
First of all, latent space is determined.
The epistemology field of these
LM systems, right.
What they can and cannot see or for us,
what they can and cannot say.
So they really are circumscribing
the boundaries of what
written words are even able to appear.
Especially as, you know,
we're thinking about all of the content
that they're being trained on.
It's a way of ordering
and processing that information.
All of that cultural memory,
pretty much that has become unmanageable.
So how is it taking books,
articles, wiki pages
and putting training that
so that it becomes
circumscribed into particular formations
in the latent space?
He also talks about image operations
through vectorization.
And a quick explanation for
that is basically,
you know, when we are training these llms,
they can't
read the strings of text themselves.
They have to turn them into
numerical vectors,
which then it does functions
and operations with that.
So it can actually allow for operations
that aren't necessarily possible
or possible in the way we understand them
when we're just writing with our own
hands, though,
doing different things with them,
which also then forces us to rethink
the concepts
we use to describe, in my terms,
literary analysis.
Right? How are we going to rethink?
Metaphors or synonyms or alliteration?
Even these simple concepts,
then, are kind of reconfigured
when they become the output of llms,
and that is completely determined
by the latent space.
He also proposes an interesting concept
around the latent space as a meta archive.
But then, rather than an archive
which you think is based
in the performances
of preservation of text
or retrieval of it,
the LM then is or like the latent
space is in transforming that rather
than preserving those original texts.
So what this translation
in this meta archive look for text.
He doesn't answer those questions.
And that's something
I'm curious about in my own research.
So how do we actually go about trying
to offer
some theory of latent spaces
for literary culture and text?
I want to pull from
another really interesting thinker for me,
Hannah Speyer.
And he, in his own article on surface
reading,
pulls into another critic,
into his discussion, Wilhelm Flusser.
And he says Flusser emphasizes
negotiating the relationship
between surface and depth by beginning
from the surface rather than the depth,
for only the phenomenon of service
can provide the intuition
that the abstract knowledge
of technical substructure cannot.
So even if we have some abstract knowledge
of how this latent space
is configured, how the LMS function,
you actually might get a better sense
by looking at the surface.
And for me, that's, you know,
like the textual output of these LMS
to create a start,
to build a technical imagination
of what
the latent space actually looks like.
So with
this set, obviously you can't extrapolate
from a single example of a little output,
but that doesn't mean you shouldn't.
You should disregard all examples, right?
I think that still seeing various ones
then starts to build those tools
of a technical imagination
that I'm trying to achieve
to better to get a better sense
of what these latent spaces look like.
And here I have Ross Godwin's one
The Road, Ryan Hauser's generated
Poetry on top, and Boyer's Berlin Miami,
which are all
generated text based on certain
inputs and certain restrictions.
What's interesting is that
I also chose these three
because there's all critical
writing about all of them.
And what's interesting
in all this critical writing about this
LM generated writing is that they agree
on a lot of things where there's perhaps
like overly correct details, but sometimes
to the detriment of the actual writing,
that there is cohesion,
but not a full like coherency.
Right?
I'm not a full artistic unity
within the work.
Sometimes it's fragmented
and sometimes it becomes two smooth.
And so these cohesion and patterns
are implied or almost over implied.
But it doesn't
get to a full, continuous narrative.
And so my work
aims to extend this research,
but also complicated because
what I'm looking at with compressed
cinema, as I'll go into and explain,
is that all of these works
that I'm showing here are based on these
sample
in training samples
that do have some sense of like coherency
and artistic unity
right there for its full science fiction.
All of these training for one, the road,
there's actually a road trip with sensors
that sense, as the car goes
to generate the output.
And so there is some sense of continuity
here.
Press cinema is a little bit different.
So comparison is an art book of film
stills by Casey Reyes
with captions by Allison Parrish.
But all of these are AI generated
or AI assisted in some way.
And I'm especially interested
in the captions for works, is that Reyes
took existing films
and then created sets of images
based on them by way of generating
generative adversarial networks.
Then Parrish
looked at those film stills
she composed herself.
Quote in putting from her dense,
minimalist descriptions of each image
spread.
But then she took the mask
filling functionality of Facebook's
AI Bart model to then
Italy, uncompressed those descriptions.
So the film the images are compressed
from original films,
and then Parrish writes the captions and
then compresses those with an LM model.
Bart the very dense captions.
You can see this in one example that
she gave of a free uncompressed caption.
The paints buckled a shoulders
thermocline and elbows tint full crook
night sheared off, drools
a golden geode, then waltzes.
So while it's specific in its phrasing,
each phrase itself is unconventional,
ambiguous, and interpretation,
so it's dense in the way
it allows an abundance
of meaning in these laconic fragments.
So then she uses Bart to uncompressed
those and expand them outwards.
Bart is a bidirectional
and autoregressive transformer,
so it kind of combines two functionalities
of machine learning models.
So bidirectional encoder
is basically look at a fragment of text
where some parts of it
have been snipped out, and they try to
guess where they've been snipped out
and what those blank spaces
might look like in autoregressive decoder
then, is a little bit different,
where it's given a string of text
and is supposed to complete
like the next likely word.
So think of, you know,
like when you're texting
and it suggests a word that's similar to
what an auto regressive
decoder is doing
when you put them together, then
say that you're given that caption
I just read aloud from parish.
The Bart model would look at it be like,
I think there's some missing spaces here.
I think they're here, here and here.
And then the model also goes,
okay, well, based on
what else is going around in the passage,
I think that the empty spaces
should have the words XYZ.
So then uncompressed is also interesting
in that parish's
fragments, what Bart might see is tokens
that have been masked
or eliminated to some extent,
or in fact the original text.
Right?
So even while uncompressed, a file
is generally to return detailed
information to it, perish
this assumption in her generating process.
So what do these captions
actually look like?
What I find interesting is that
even though they are so fragmented,
they're not, you know, this continuous
narrative, right?
They're like fragmented captions
of discrete parts of the narrative.
It then starts to converge, similar
to what we see in those
other examples of LM generated text.
I claim that they established
sensory detail, scene and characters,
even while her initial fragments don't
necessarily seem to try to do that. So
the sentences
discuss crystalline mouthparts
that are soft and shiny and soak,
and the sun begins to lighten
and the rain stops.
And so, while it's not connected to
an obvious narrative, these lines conjure
wet greenery, the interest to cease
between rain and sign and light
reflecting off of the do.
Or there's a scenery
in terms of a church, a large Gothic
Revival stained glass window which adds
to the intensity of the imagery,
and the narrative continues
that this is where they live.
The pillars mutter look, which locates
this place containing pillars
which are commonly found in Gothic
Revival architecture.
Right.
And then there's also some sense
of characterization around the pillars.
The narrator comments.
Salt peers around the room
and raises his face
to the ceiling and gazes in disgust.
So if we extrapolate from the one pre
uncompressed writing sample
that Parrish gives us, she's not concerned
in presenting a clear narrative,
but in reading the final Bartosz
version, it's hard to ignore the gestures
towards such a possibility.
On the sentence level, we can surmise
why the individual components of the story
will emerge.
Makes sense that a lot of
the original text was surrealistic images,
so it makes sense that Bart would choose
to repeat this with more sensory imagery.
But even if
all of this has some gesture
towards possibility,
the fact that Bart picks up
on these individual elements of character
and scene is some specific choice
determined by the latent space.
So Parrish does uncompressed
racist films in a particular way
by reintroducing that sensory detail,
environment and character driven action.
So there's
some sense of narrative ness,
even while it's not a full narrative.
And what I think is especially weird
is that this is where it becomes
it comes from a logical fragments
rather than logical continuity
like we see in those other examples.
The way that the latent space vectorize
as input text, it's
circumscribed as the possible outputs
of what is even available to be generated,
and it by transforming
rather than preserving the text that's
trained on it, produces similar forms
throughout various options of input text.
It starts to move towards
a similar output.
And so I have a quote
which I think is actually really helpful.
Overview of lens by three blue one brown,
where I suggest that maybe
latent space is latent spaces are encoding
these higher level concepts
cast just like the name of a thing or what
a noun is, but maybe larger narrative
ness qualities are encoded.
And thank you.
That's all I have for my presentation.